<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An argument concerning the human souls seperate [sic] subsistance</title>
            <author>Layton, Henry, 1622-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L755A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34962</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14916613</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14916613</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102903</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49841)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102903)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1573:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An argument concerning the human souls seperate [sic] subsistance</title>
                  <author>Layton, Henry, 1622-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Layton by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spira respirans.</term>
               <term>Soul.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:102903:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ARGUMENT Concerning the Human Souls ſeperate Subſiſtance.</head>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>The PREFACE.</head>
               <p>IN the Month of <hi>December, 1698.</hi> A Neighbour reputed a Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, came to me, and brought in his Hand a ſmall Pamphlet, whoſe Title was <hi>Spira Reſpirans,</hi> and delivering the ſame unto me, he told me that there were divers Arguments in it, for proving the Souls ſeparate Subſiſtance, which he perceived I ſtood in doubt of. I liked his charitable Inclination for drawing Men out of Error, or the uneaſineſs of a doubting Condition, and upon peruſal of his Treatiſe, did find that it medled not with this Subject, until the very latter end of the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, or the <hi>48</hi> page of it, from whence my Examination begins. And thereby I found that he produces three Arguments for the Souls ſeparate Subſiſtance. The two firſt whereof I thought to be fancyful or enthuſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, and therefore I have made very ſhort Anſwers to them. But his Third Argument I found to be more ſober and ſubſtantial, and drawn from two principal Topicks. The firſt of them from the Reſurrection; and the ſecond from Gods creating of Souls for Men, and to each of them I have made a diſtinct Anſwer, and more at large then to both his former, and therein have ſatisfyed my own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding; and yet I remain under a deſire to hear the judgment of other Men upon this Subject, and force of the Arguments herein ſpecifyed. I believe that
<pb facs="tcp:102903:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102903:3"/>the Precept delivered in <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, of not ſeeing Sin or Error in our Brethren without reproving them for it, is in full practice at this Day. And as I have taken my ſhare in doing, ſo I expect a ſhare in ſuffering, according to the Tenor thereof. If I might chuſe the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of being reproved, it ſhould be done with Love, and in the Spirit of Meekneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but if that cannot be obtained, I will rather adventure the being laſh'd or ſpatter'd with the Dirt of Reproaches (as I have once before been) then to continue in Error, or ſuch a ſtate of doubting as I have long been under, concerning the nature of the Subject here put under Examination. And therefore I expoſe the preſent Pamphlet to the publick View, with ſubmiſſion to the tryal of other Mens judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereupon. And ſhall ſay no more to my conſiderate Reader, then that I wiſh him heartily to Farewel.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102903:3"/>
            <head>Spira Reſpirans, <hi>Lond.</hi> printed 1695. in 8vo.</head>
            <p>Pag. 48. THE Writer of that Pamphlet ſays, there are ſome few honeſt Hearts who perſwade themſelves, and would have others perſwaded, that the Soul is mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and dies with the Body.</p>
            <p>And in kindneſs to theſe honeſt Perſons, he intends here to prove, that the Soul doth indeed live when ſeparated from the Body, and that therefore it is immortal. In proving of which Aſſertion he ſuppoſes as granted, that there is in Man a Bodily being and a Spiritual being, ſo diſtinct one from another, as that they are beings of a different Nature, and devidable one of them from another, with a continuance of ſubſiſtance to them both. And his ſo doing, I ſay, is but begging, and not proving the point now in queſtion between us For the honeſt Hearts to whom he writes, do deny that there is ſuch a ſpiritual Being or Subſtance in Man, as is utterly immaterial, or that hath any ſuch being of it ſelf, as that it can ſubſiſt in a ſtate of ſeparation from the Body.</p>
            <p>His part in the diſpute of this Queſtion ſhould have been, firſt to prove that there is ſuch a ſpiritual being in Man as he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuppoſed. And becauſe he hath not done ſo, nor made any Overtures or Offers towards it, and his Opponents will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of his Suppoſitions, that there is ſuch a Spirit in Man as he hath ſurmiſed, all his Arguments founded upon that ſurmiſe, fall and fail of themſelves for want of a real and true Foundation for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102903:4"/>the ſupport of them, and need no farther Anſwer till he ſhall have better proved that there is ſuch a Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it in Man as he before but ſuppoſed.</p>
            <p>P. 50. He ſays, the Nature being or whatneſs of a Soul or Mind is thinking, and nothing elſe but thinking, and thinking is all it doth or hath: I anſwer, that his Words; the being or whatneſs of the Soul, do, I conceive intend its Eſſence, or even the very ſubſtance of it which ſuits better to his Words, the whatneſs of it, as if in Truth it had no other ſubſtance but thinking.</p>
            <p>If he ſhall prove that there is really ſuch a ſpiritual ſubſtance in Man as he hath ſuppoſed, it will then be time to argue with him concerning this whatneſs of thinking, which he pretends to be the very eſſence and ſubſtance of it. But till ſuch proof ſhall be made his ſubſtantial ſpiritual Soul, and the whatneſs of it ſhall be left, as the chimerical apprehenſions of our preſent Writer. He diſcourſes here further concerning what uſe the Soul makes of the Body, which I paſs as impertinent until he prove there is in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſuch a ſort of Soul as he ſurmiſes.</p>
            <p>P. 52. He ſays many of our Thoughts depend upon the Union of the Soul and Body and come by occaſion of bodily things, but yet that all our thoughts do not do ſo. But I think the contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> that all our thoughts and power of thinking ariſe from, and depend upon the Union of the Soul and Body. <hi>David</hi> tells us, that let the intentions of a wicked Man be never ſo bad, yet when he dies, all his thoughts periſh. And <hi>Job</hi> ſays, that in the Grave the weary are at reſt, and Men are there freed from all ſort of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; and I demand of our opponents one Hiſtorical Inſtance or Narrative of a ſeparate Souls thinking, or doing any thing elſe, from the time of the Worlds Creation to this Day, believing they cannot produce ſuch an inſtance, excepting Parables like thoſe of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and the Rapture or Revelation of St. <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 53. He ſays that it is Gods Will the Soul ſhould continue to be immortal, and this he promiſes clearly to prove by his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Arguments which come now to be examined.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102903:4"/>
            <p>He draws his firſt Argument from his own Experience, and ſays that in a Trance when he was not ſenſible whether he was alive or dead, he thought, unde ſtood, conſider'd and will'd, and more vigorouſly then ordinary; and becauſe he did then do ſo, he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues why may not dead Men continue to do ſo? I anſwer, becauſe there is a great deal of difference betwixt a Man in a Trance and one perfectly dead, and as much as between a living and dead Perſon; and I conceive one may as well argue, a living Man thinks, underſtands, conſiders and wills, and why may not a dead Man do ſo.</p>
            <p>P. 55. Secondly, he ſays it is my Duty to love God, and to love him ſtill, and therefore my capacity of loving God ſhall never ceaſe, to which I reply, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltra eſſe non datur poſſe.</hi> He ſays further, Bodies do not think, cannot love, it is only Souls that can, to which I anſwer, that neither Bodies nor Souls in ſeparation one from another can think, or love, or do any thing elſe whatſoever; and I deſire to be informed of the contrary, by any that know of ſuch things ſeparately done; and without the conjunction of them both together.</p>
            <p>P. 56. He ſays God is not prais'd by Bodies but by Souls; I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, not by Souls without Bodies, but by Men, he is praiſed du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Conjunction of their Souls and Bodies, but by the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of that Union, all human actions looſe their Power and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, which by the Reſurrection ſhall at laſt be reſtored with greater Capacities than before were enjoyed. He ſays he deſires to love God perpetually, and for ever, I cannot blame him for it; for whilſt he can do ſo, he ſhall have a perpetual ſecurity from the ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oke of Death, concerning which the Hymn of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> when he was drawn out of the jaws of Death, doth ſufficiently inſtruct us. He ſays he cannot deſire any Good, but God wills it as much or more I reply, he may lawfully deſire a good and large Eſtate, with deſign and intent to deſtribute liberally to the Poor, but neither I, nor he, do think God oblig'd to will as he wills in this point, or many other like occaſions.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:102903:5"/>
            <p>P. 57. He demands, would God give Man a deſire to a good thing, and not give him the good thing deſired. I reply, God gives and allows to Men the deſire of many good things, which he gives them not the power to attain unto. He quotes our Lords directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to pray, and promiſes that whatſoever we pray for in his Name, he will give us. Whence he may as well warrant the good ſucceſs of a Prayer, requeſting him to give us <hi>Fortunatus</hi>'s <hi>Purſe,</hi> or ſomething equivalent thereunto.</p>
            <p>P. 51. He ſays there are in the Scripture ſufficient Evidences, if not ſelf evident proof that the Soul is immortal. I reply, I have not yet been ſo fortunate as to meet with ſufficient Evidence to that purpoſe in the Scripture, and much leſs with thoſe ſelf-evident proofs which he ſays may be found there. And I lay very much blame upon him for not producing ſuch Evidences and Self-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Arguments as he knows to be there, for the Conviction of thoſe honeſt Hearts for whoſe ſakes he hath invented all theſe Arguments of his own, and which have very little force or coerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in them.</p>
            <p>The third Argument, which he calls his laſt for proof of the Souls Immortality, he draws from the nature and manner of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; and ſays that if the Soul die and periſh with the Body, then at the reſurrection, the Soul which riſes cannot be the ſame with that which dyed, but one newly created for informing the riſing Body, and which cannot be conſcious of what was done in the perſon formerly dead, and ſo not deſerving Reward or Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for works done by the Perſon now riſing in his former Soul and Body. To this I reply, that nothing can have a real and true reſurrection to Life, which was not really and truly dead before. And therefore if the Soul have a real and true Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection at the laſt day, it muſt have had a true and real Death periſhing or extinguiſhment before that time. Whence if it be to have a true and future Reſurrection, it muſt die and periſh with the Body. whoſe amicable concomitant it always is both in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, at the Birth, in the Life, at the Death, and in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Perſon. And as to the ſameneſs of that Soul with that that periſhed at the death; it ſhall be as much the ſame,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102903:5"/>as the Body riſing ſhall be the ſame with that that dyed. And herein I do further conceive, that we cannot properly hold a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning the Reſurrection of the Body or the Soul ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately conſider'd, there being nothing either in Reaſon or Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, upon which Men can ground their Apprehenſions of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of either of them ſeparate from the other. But if we will ſpeak properly and truly of the Reſurrection, we muſt ſay with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. that it is the Reſurrection of the Dead, not of the Body or Soul, but of the Perſon which comprehends them both as the two main and conſtituent parts thereof. He ſays there v. 32. If the dead riſe not, <hi>let us eat and drink for too mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row we dye.</hi> (And there is an end of us) then he demands, if the Dead be raiſed, with what Bodies do they come? without making any enquiry concerning the Soul, which I conceive he paſt as a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary principle which muſt give Life to the Body, and conſtitute the ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed Perſon. The Apoſtles Creed in our Language, delivers as an Article of Faith the Reſurrection of the Body, but in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it de arts from its originals, both of the Greek and Latin Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages in the expreſs words of both which, it is called and termed the Reſurrection of the Fleſh. I find no ſufficient reaſon why this variance from our Originals ſhould be continued amongſt us, and do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſh the Correction or Amendment of it, believing withal, that the beſt and moſt proper expreſſion of our Faith in this point uſed in the Niceen-creed by the words I look for the Reſurrection of the Dead, by which I conceive is intended the dead perſons conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted of Souls and Bodies; the ſame, or after the ſame ſort and manner as they formerly liv'd in this World, able to account for all they did whilſt they before lived here, and to receive juſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compences according to their Works done in this Life. Here, when Men dye, they are commonly ſaid to ſleep with their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the faithful eſpecially are ſaid to dye in the Lord, and to reſt from their Labours 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. <hi>They are ſaid to ſleep in Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> directs to remember theſe days of darkneſs, for that they ſhall be many, and therefore we muſt remember them, that we may be prepared for them, by keeping our Lights and Lamps burning and ſhining, till death extinguiſh them and our ſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, by caſting all into that ſound ſleep which Death only can afford us, giving us thereby a perfect Reſt from all Oppreſſions,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102903:6"/>Maladies, Temptations and Troubles. Of which Men have an Umbrage or Similitude when they ſee Men folded in a very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and ſound Sleep, out of which with pinching or beating they can with great difficulties be awaked. And yet we find that Men rouſed out of ſuch a Sleep, after they have rubbed their Byes, and have been throughly awakened, can give a ready and reaſonable account of the things which they have done before their falling aſleep. And of a like Nature with the rouſing from ſuch a Sleep, I conceive the Reſurrection of the Dead will be. And if any Man will ſtill be ſo curious, as to puzzle himſelf and his opponent with the nice demands of how, and by what means ſuch things ſhall be done, and would deſire me to account <hi>de modo reſurrectionis,</hi> and the means by which it ſhall be acted and performed; I ſhall only, giving the ſatisfaction of a <hi>deus providebit,</hi> referring for the reſt to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. as the beſt and largeſt account which I know to be given concerning it, and as a parallel caſe thereunto I will point him to <hi>Jo</hi> 3. where our Lord diſcourſing with <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> tells him, <hi>the Wind bloweth where it liſteth, and thou heareſt the ſound thereof, but cauſt not tell whence it cometh, nor whither it goeth, ſo is every one that is born of the Spirit. Nicodemus</hi> replys, <hi>how can theſe things be?</hi> And ſo I think may every Man reaſonably do, who will nicely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the points really conſiderable in our great myſtery of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Dead. If Men could reaſonably diſcover and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for the modes and manner of ſuch a Reſurrection, it would need no more to be accounted amongſt the great myſteries of Chriſtian Religion, as in all times it hath been eſteemed. We have a Faith next unto Knowledge, that our Lords humane Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was procreated in a Virgin without the Knowledge or Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a Man, and I may as reaſonably enquire <hi>de modo hujus generationis,</hi> and after what manner the ſame was acted or came to paſs. Again, my Writer and I, and all that I know are agreed, that the humane Perſon is acted and moved, either by a ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial intelligent Soul, or by a Superfine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et material and unintelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Spirit, but neither of us, nor I think any Man elſe can tell any thing, <hi>de modo movendi,</hi> or after what manner, and by what means either of them doth or can act and move the wonderful Machine of the human Body. Theſe Sciences are juſtly to be ranked <hi>inter arcana opificis.</hi> God hath not yet revealed unto Men
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102903:6"/>the manner and means of ſuch performances, and there ſeems to be a nimium in the re-ſearches of thoſe Men, who may pretend to make ſtrict and nice enquiries into the manner and nature of ſuch myſteries, or <hi>de modo operationis</hi> thereof. It ſeems enough for Men to know, God hath declared and promiſed, that there ſhall be an univerſal Reſurrection of the Dead, human Perſons of all ſorts, without making any ſuch Declaration or Promiſe to any other ſort of Creature whatſoever. And for this reaſon the Brutes are called the Beaſts that periſh utterly, which Doctrine may be, and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where hath been proved by me from a clear current of Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in the Old Teſtament, and by a potent and ſtrong ſtream of Teſtimonies in the New.</p>
            <p>P. 59. He ſays that if the preſent human Soul dye, or periſh with the Body, then there muſt be a new Soul created for the riſing Body, at the time of its Reſurrection, which Soul cannot reaſonably be accountable for acts done in the former Body, or by the perſon which now is to be rais'd. To this I reply. That this Argument is founded upon a Fallacy or Miſtake of the Writer, whoſe conſequence would be apparently fallacious, if he do not firſt pretend to believe that <hi>Adam</hi> had a Soul, as well, and as particularly created for him as his Body. And therefore this point ſhall be a little further examined; to which purpoſe ſhall be quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. <hi>God formed Man of the Duſt of the Ground, and breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into his Noſtrils the Breath of Life, and Man became a living Soul.</hi> As a Preliminary to this Examination, I pretend to have it gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me, that the words Man became a living Soul, do intend or ſignifie the ſame thing as if it had been ſaid that Man became a living Perſon. That the word Soul in Scripture doth commonly and even ordinarily ſignifie the Perſon; I am able to prove by many hundred Inſtances, where the ſame cannot be intended to ſignifie any other then an humane Perſon. <hi>Abraham</hi> going with his Wife into <hi>Egypt,</hi> directs her to ſay ſhe was his Siſter, for by that means, he ſays, his Soul ſhall live for her ſake, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> they ſhould ſave him alive for her ſake, or he ſhould ſtill remain a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Perſon, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.20. <hi>Lot interceeds ſon the</hi> preſervation of <hi>Zoar,</hi> ſaying, <hi>this City is near to flee unto, and it is a little One, O let me eſcape thither, (is it not a little one) and my Soul ſhall live, (i. e.)</hi> I ſhall live, or ſtill remain a living Perſon. So when <hi>Jacob</hi> went down into <hi>Egypt,</hi> he carryed with him Seventy Souls And
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102903:7"/>
               <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s two Sons which were born to him before that time, are called two Souls. So <hi>Acts</hi> 27.37. In St. <hi>Pauls</hi> dangerous Voyage, there were with him in the Ship, 276 Souls. I ſay, that in theſe places, and many hundred other places in the Scripture, the word Soul cannot intend or ſignifie any other thing then Perſon, by one of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e moſt ordinary <hi>Synecdoches</hi> in the World, <hi>viz. partis pro toto,</hi> where, by the moſt active and living part of the Perſon, the whole Perſon is intended and ſignified.</p>
            <p>I pretend then, that leaving the figurative expreſſion of this Text, it may be thus read according to the true intent of it, God breathed into <hi>Adam</hi> the Breath of Life, and he became a living Perſon. And thereupon I obſerve, that there is expreſs mention made here of the Creation of Mans Body, but that there is no mention at all of creating a Soul for him. But God breathed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Noſtrils the Breath of Life, and thereupon I conceive, that God who had then newly created and finiſhed his Organical Body, had made his Blood and Humors pullulent, and ready to be tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and raiſed into a flame, by the acting or fanning of ſuch a moderate Breath as was intended to be breathed into him for that purpoſe; whence God breathed into him the Breath of Life, by whoſe fanning the Blood, and Humors then pullulent and ready for that operation were tinded and kindled into a flame or glowing, which from that time, continued and reſided in the Blood and Humors of the Body, acting and moving <hi>Adams</hi> whole Body and every part, Member, and Muſcle of the ſame, the ſame flame of Life being fanned and revived every moment; by the guſts of the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bient Air drawn through the Lungs to fann and refreſh the flame of Life reſiding about the Heart, and the other moſt eminent and vital parts and viſcera of the Body. And this Breath continued to be abſolutely neceſſary for theſe purpoſes during the time of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> whole Life; and when he begat a Sen in his own likeneſs, his Seed by commixtion, <hi>in loco Idoneo,</hi> became coagulated, and by the neceſſary fomentation thereof fermented, and in its due time became a vegitative and living Maſs, which by degrees grew to an embrion, which daily received ſome degrees of growth and motion, and when by ſuch vegitation and growth it had obtained its due perfection, it ſought by inſtinct and found paſſage through its Mother to the open Air, which after it hath once received, it cannot live without it; for that upon failour of fanning by the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102903:7"/>ambient Air, after it hath once received the ſame, it fails and dyes again, neceſſarily within the ſpace or compaſs of ſome few Moments. And of this our daily Experience fully aſſures us, by the ſudden Death of thoſe who paſs out of this World, by Hanging or Strugling, which proves, the want of this Breath to be a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and ſure cauſe of Death. Phyſicians have told us, that if after the Childs perfection, the Mother be ript open, and the Child be taken from her in the Secondines, it may live ſome Hours after without aſſiſtance from this Breath of Life, but that after once it hath received this Breath, whereby the flame of Life and Glowing of the Blood hath been kindled in it, it can never af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, live many Moments without ſuch fanninig of the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Air, drawn in through the Lungs as hath before been deſcribed.</p>
            <p>An Umbrage or Similitude of this Operation, we may read in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Viſion of the dry Bones of which there was a vaſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, then there was a ſhaking, and the Bones came together, Bone to his Bone, then Fleſh was ſuper-induced over the Bones, with the Arteries, Sinues and Veins, and all the reſt of the Viſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ra, to humane Bodies belonging, after which the Skin was drawn o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them all, and yet they were ſtill but dead Carcaſtes; becauſe (as the Text ſays) there was no Breath in them. And therefore God directs the Pophet, ſaying, propheſie unto the Winds, and ſay, thus ſaith the Lord, come from the four Winds O Breath, and breath upon theſe ſlain that they may live; and upon the Prophets doing ſo as he was directed, the Breath came into them, and they lived and ſtood up upon their Feet an exceeding great Army; ſo as by the Winds breathing this Breath of Life, and fanning the ſtems of their pullulent Blood and Humors, the flame of Life was tinded and kindled in them, by the Vertue and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of which, they all a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe, ſtood up upon their Feet, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came living Perſons, in the very ſame manner as <hi>Adam</hi> before had done. And thus may be ſpared and ſaved that vaſt imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which Men have needleſly put upon God, of making or creating new Souls every day, for all the ſeveral procreations, in the World that bear the figure of a humane Shape, be the coiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons never ſo unlawful or beſtial. The ſort of Soul laſt before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, ſuits well with <hi>Moſes</hi> Text concerning <hi>Adams</hi> Creation, and agrees punctually with the reſurrection of <hi>Ezekiels</hi> dry Bones, and is a very probable and likely Specimen of that Reſurrection,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102903:8"/>which Men expect at the laſt Day, and which we may look for with as great certainty, as that there will be a too Morrow after the day now paſſing. St. <hi>Paul</hi> thus teſtifying, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.13. <hi>If there be no Reſurrection of the Dead, our Teaching is Vain, and your Faith is alſo Vain, ye are yet in your Sinns, and all they that are fallen aſleep in Chriſt are periſhed.</hi> Whence it ſeems conſequent, that the expectations of future Recompenſes to Chriſtians, is founded upon the reſurrection of the Dead, and if that could or ſhould poſſibly happen to fail us, it would make the whole Chriſtian Religion an Oeconomy, to become a vain pretence, and of no benefit at all to them who profeſs it. And our Apoſtle proceeds further upon this point to <hi>verſ.</hi> 29. and there, in further proof of the Reſurrection he ſays, <hi>if in this Life only we have hope in Chriſt,</hi> we are of all Men moſt miſerable, and the reaſon why Chriſtians would be ſo, is becauſe that in this Life they are obliged to deny themſelves, and to mortifie, and ſometimes to crucifie the Fleſh with its Affections and Luſts, which Men do in expectation of great Rewards, and avoiding puniſhments promiſed and threatned in a future ſlate to come after this Life is ended, all which are here applyed to prove a neceſſity and certainty of the Reſurrection of the Dead. Then ſtill the Apoſtle goes on to verſ. 32. where he ſays, <hi>If I have fought with Beaſts at</hi> Epheſus, <hi>what advantageth it me if the Dead riſe not? Let us eat and drink for too morrow we dye,</hi> plainly intending, that let Men ſuffer what they will for the Name and Faith of Chriſt, thoſe ſufferings ſhall profit them nothing, unleſs there be a Reſurrection of the Dead. And then, the Apoſtle proceeds to ſay ſomething concerning the manner of this Reſurrection, and to give further proof of the ſame from other Topicks. And the ſame Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. directs the Diſciples not to ſorrow very much for their dead Friends, becauſe they ſhall have a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; thoſe who ſleep with Jeſus, ſhall Chriſt bring with him at his ſecond coming, after he hath raiſed them by the voice of the Arch-Angel and the trump of God, and then ſhall they be caught up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Clouds to meet the Lord in the Air, and ſo ſhall we ever be with the Lord, adding, comfort one another with theſe words. He doth not ſay, comfort your ſelves or one another with the hopes or expectations of your dead Friends Souls being gone to Heaven; although if that were a Truth and known to him, I think he could not reaſonably, or even poſſibly have omitted it in this place. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.16. <hi>The Lord give Mercy to the Houſe of</hi> Oneſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102903:8"/>the Lord grant unto him, that he may find Mercy of the Lord in that day <hi>chap.</hi> 4.7. <hi>I have fought a good fight,</hi> &amp;c. and henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Lord the righteous Judge ſhall give me at that day, and not to me only, but to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them who love his appearing, which words plainly intend our Lords ſecond coming. Whence that day muſt intend the laſt Judgment. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Rejoyce in as much as ye are made partakers of Chriſts Suffering, that when his Glory ſhall be revealed, ye may be glad alſo with exceeding great Joy.</hi> cap. 5.4. He exho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts the Elders to be careful in their Offices, <hi>and when the chief Shepherd ſhall appear ye ſhall receive a Crown of Glory that fadeth not away.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3 The ſame Apoſtle exhorts ſeeing the earthly World and all that is in it ſhall be burnt up and diſſolved, what manner of Perſons ought ye to be in all holy Converſation and Godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, looking for and haſting unto the coming of the day of God, which though it be terrible to others, ſhall to them be a great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence and Reward, without mentioning an intermediate State of departed Souls 1 <hi>John</hi> 2 28. He exhorts the Diſciples to abide in Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt, <hi>that when ye ſhall appear, ye may have Confidence, and not be aſhamed before him at his Coming.</hi> cap. 3.2. <hi>Beloved, now are we the Sons of God, and it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be, but we know that when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is,</hi> mentioning no expectations of future Recompences till our Lords ſecond Coming, and time of our own Reſurrection when we ſhall ſee him as he is, and be made like unto him. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.7. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts the Diſciples, that under all their Afflictions they ſhould be patient unto the coming of the Lord, which he ſays draws nigh, without mentioning of any Reward after Death, untill the Coming of the Lord. And thus I have quoted a cloud of knowing Witneſſes, to prove that the hope of Recompences future to this Life, is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the firm Rock of the Reſurrection, and Chriſts coming to Judgment without mention of a ſeparate ſtate of Souls, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ermediate Recompences between Death and Judgment; and to ſtrengthen the Hope and Belief of thoſe few honeſt Hearts, which our Writer has us'd his beſt endeavour to over throw and pervert. We read <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.17. God ſays to <hi>Noah, I do bring a flood of Waters upon the Earth to deſtroy all Fleſh wherein is the Breath of Life,</hi> c 7.22. <hi>All in whoſe Noſtrils was the Breath of Life, of all that was in the dry Land dyed.</hi> I conceive theſe Texts do very well explain
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102903:9"/>what is meant or intended by the Words. God breath'd into <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> Noſtrils the breath of Life, whereby he preſently became a living Perſon. It ſeems ſuch a Breath as tinded and kindled in his Blood and Humours, and the ſtems thereof that flame, or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Life which immediately acted his organical Body, and gave Life and Motion thereunto, and continued to perform that Office in him during the whole time of his Life, and in no other manner then it is known to do among the Beaſts that periſh. The breath of all their Noſtrils was ſtopt by ſuffocation in that deluge, and thereby was fully verified what is ſaid by <hi>Solomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 3.19. concerning Men and Beaſts, <hi>as the one dyeth, ſo dyeth the other, yea, they have all one Breath.</hi> So that (herein) a Man hath no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence above a Beaſt, all are of the Duſt, and all turn to Duſt again, and who knoweth the Spirit of a Man that goeth upward, or the Spirit of a Beaſt that goeth downward to the Earth. By which it ſeems he did not know there was ſuch a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Spirits of Men and Beaſts, yet that there was among the Men of his time an Opinion or Conjecture, that there was or might be ſuch a difference between the Spirits of Men and Beaſts, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which, he demands, who knows the truth of it? Which ſeems pregnant with this Negative, that no Man doth with any clearneſs, know whether there be ſuch a difference between their Spirits or not; after which he ſays, <hi>chap.</hi> 12.7. That when Men dye, <hi>The Duſt ſhall return to the Earth as it was, and the Spirit ſhall return to God who gave it</hi> In his third chap. the matter is argued more at length, and with greater deliberation, whereas the latter ſeems but a ſudden Expreſſion, and without a ſerious debating upon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but thereunto I have made a larger Anſwer in another Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.29. <hi>David</hi> ſays to God, <hi>Thou hideſt thy Face, they are troubled, thou takeſt away their Breath, they dye, and return to their Duſt, viz.</hi> The Children of Men do ſo. Iſa. 2.22. <hi>Ceaſe ye from Man whoſe Breath is in his Neſtrils, for wherein is he to be accounted of?</hi> Dan. 5.23. <hi>Daniel</hi> ſays to <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> thou haſt highly honoured thy pup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit Gods, <hi>but the God in whoſe Hand is thy Breath thou haſt not glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified.</hi> Acts 17.25. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the Athenians, that God needs not their Service, or any thing elſe that the World has in it, ſeeing he giveth to all Life, and Breath, and all things. Upon which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that the expreſſions of Life and Breath, if they be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignificant,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102903:9"/>are of a ſimilar Nature one to another, and may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Breath which gives Life. A Spirit of the ſame Nature with that which God breathed into <hi>Adams</hi> Noſtrils at the time of his Creation.</p>
            <p>By the Texts before quoted, I ſtand at the preſent convinced, that the Breath of Life which God breathed into <hi>Adams</hi> Noſtrils was not an immaterial intelligent ſubſtance; but was of a ſimilar Nature to that before quoted. <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.22. where it is ſaid, <hi>all in whoſe Noſtrils was the Breath of Life dyed;</hi> and ſuch as was prophetical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call'd for by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> to come from the four Winds a Breath, to breath upon thoſe ſlain Perſons, (now ready for Life) that they might live. The Breath of Life which by God was breathed into <hi>Adams Noſtrils,</hi> I yet conceive, (as I have before delivered) to have been common Air breathed into him in ſuch a moderate Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as might kindle and inflame his Blood and Humours, and the ſtems of them ready and ripe for that operation and activity, which the Spirits of Blood ſo kindled might impart to them; and that it was not an extraneous ſubſtantial intelligent Spirit created by God at that time, and for that purpoſe. And I am ready and deſirous to put the whole ſtate of the Controverſie upon the true and clear de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding of this Queſtion, being ready to grant, that if God did create a new ſubſtantial intelligent Spirit for that purpoſe, and infuſed the ſame into <hi>Adams</hi> Body for the informing thereof at his Creation, that then it is likely he may ſo continue to do, and create new Souls for all perſons procreated in humane ſhapes all the World over, and in all ages of it from <hi>Adams</hi> Creation to our preſent time. But if that Breath of Life which God breathed into <hi>Adams</hi> Noſtrils was only for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the common ambient Air, breathed into him with a fitting moderation for tinding and kindling the flame of Life in his Blood and Humours, and the ſtems thereof then ripe and ready for that O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, then it is likely that God did neither form and make a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial intelligent Spirit for the acting of <hi>Adams</hi> Body, nor that he hath created ſuch Spirits for Men in the Ages following, but that rather ſuch ſubſtantial intelligent Spirits have drawn their Original from the apprehenſions and Imaginations of Men, and becauſe I think the ſame to be a miſtake, I do willingly contribute my beſt endeavours for the rectification thereof, and to bring all diſputes concerning the ſame to ſuch a determination as ſhall be moſt agreeable to the tenor of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the cleareſt rules and dictates of reaſon that Men are able to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102903:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>attain unto, for the more ſudden attaining, of which end I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to put the whole Controverſie upon the determination of this ſingle point, whether God did create for <hi>Adam</hi> a ſpiritual intelligent Soul or not? If my opponents be able to prove with intelligible clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that he did ſo, then I am ready to give up unto them the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion which I maintain in this Controverſie, and if they be not able to prove the Creation before mention'd, they may (if they pleaſe) forbear further to oppoſe the maintainers of my Opinion; concluding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, that if they neither can perform one part of the demand, nor will ſubmit to the other, we ſhall ſtill be obliged to proceed on both ſides to the further examination of the whole Controverſie and thoſe many points and arguments which thereupon have riſen, and are likely to be referred to a further Examination and Determination.</p>
            <p>P. 59 He ſays he is well able to prove the eſſence of the Soul to be thinking by fundamental arguments, but refuſes to do it now, becauſe he ſays it is beſide his preſent purpoſe. But I differ in Opinion, and think if he be able to do it, that proof will ever be to very good purpoſe, and therefore I requeſt him to beſtow his pains upon it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving yet that he will never be able to make a good performance of it, <hi>viz.</hi> that there is either ſuch a Soul in Man as he pretends, nor that thinking is the eſſence of it, allowing what he hath before ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to be true, that of that which is not there can be neither effect nor eſſence.</p>
            <p>P. 60. He would have Men to bring their Minds to ſuch an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractedneſs, as to lay aſide all thoughts of bodily things, and all thoughts that come by occaſion of Body; and then to reflect upon what you find remaining, until your Mind hath a reflex and clear knowledge of it ſelf. I conceive that this Advice tends to perſwade Men to give over all thinking upon the things which they know, and to think altogether upon they know not what, and ſo to become diſtracted, as he profeſſes he hath ſometime been.</p>
            <p>The remaining Pages of this Pamphlet, ſpeak only concerning himſelf and his own perſonal actings and ſufferings, with which I have no deſign or inclination to meddle, and therefore my Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon this Pamphlet ſhall here be concluded and finiſhed.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
